have you ever been in a chat with an AI and it feels amazing
then suddenly it forgets the most important thing you said
like you told it make it a shortlist
and three messages later it drops a giant essay anyway
or you say don't mention spoilers and it casually spoils the plot
it's tempting to think the AI is being lazy or dramatic
but most of the time
it's something way more boring and often very real
it ran out of space and that space has a name
it's the context window here's the twist
your message becomes tokens
the models replied does too
both spend the same limited budget
once you see that AI amnesia starts making a lot more sense
in the next few minutes I'll make two weird words feel normal
tokens and context window
first we'll talk about tokens
they're not exactly words
they're more like chunks of text the model works with
second we'll talk about the context window
that's the maximum amount of tokens
the model can pay attention to at one time
then we'll hit the main rule
your input tokens plus the model's output tokens
have to fit inside one shared limit in most chat setups
and finally you'll get a simple toolkit
you'll learn how to keep the AI on track
even in long chats without any coding or tech jargon
let's start with tokens because this is the part nobody explains well
when you type a message
the model doesn't truly see words the way you do
it sees tokens a token is a small chunk of text
sometimes it's a whole word
sometimes it's part of a word
sometimes it's punctuation
like a comma or a dash or three exclamation points in a row
here's a simple way to picture it
imagine your sentence is a Lego build
words are the big pieces you notice
tokens are the smaller pieces
the model snaps together behind the scenes
so if you type something like unbelievable
it might get split into a couple of chunks
instead of staying as one neat piece
and if you type wait what
the dots and punctuation can add extra tokens you didn't expect
that's why this looks short
can still be expensive and this looks long
might be cheaper than you think
people sometimes use a rough rule of thumb
like in English tokens average around four characters
that's a handy approximation
but it's not exact don't treat that like a law of physics
it varies a lot by language spacing
formatting and the exact text
the only point you need today is this
tokens are the unit the model counts
and the model has a maximum number it can handle at once
now let's talk about that maximum
the context window is the amount of text in tokens
that the model can consider at one time
while generating its next reply
I like to call it working memory
but with one big warning it's not human memory
it's more like a limited size whiteboard
you can write a bunch of stuff on the whiteboard
but once it's full you can't keep adding without erasing something
in chat the whiteboard holds the conversation so far
that includes your earlier messages
the model's earlier replies
and sometimes hidden system text or instructions
so what happens when the chat gets too long
in some apps older messages may be truncated
summarised or no longer fully visible to the model
and when the model can't see something
it can't reliably follow it
that's when you get the classic moment
you set a rule at the start
like keep it under 100 words
and later the model breaks it
not because it wants to
but because the rule might not be inside the window anymore
and yes this is a real constraint
not just bad design
processing more context generally takes more computation and memory
one more important note
some apps advertise extra features like saved memory
profile notes or retrieval from documents that can help
but the model still generates each response
based on the tokens it has in its active context
right now this is the most useful idea in the whole video
so I'm going to say it slowly
the context window is not just what you type in many chat tools
it's what you type plus what the model replies
so you and the model are basically sharing one backpack
your prompt goes in the backpack
then the model's answer goes in the same backpack
and the backpack has a fixed size
that means a long answer doesn't just cost time
it can crowd out older instructions and details
here's a situation you've probably lived
you paste a big wall of text and say
read all of this and write me a detailed 2,000 word response
the model tries it starts writing
but the more it writes the more tokens it uses
and those output tokens are eating into the same
total context capacity
so the model can end up in a weird spot where it's generating
but it no longer has room to keep the full
original instructions in view
that's why a smarter move is often ask for a tight outline first
then expand one section at a time
you're not lowering quality
you're managing the budget
think of it like ordering food
if you order everything at once
your table gets crowded and messy
if you order in courses you keep control
same information better pacing
less chaos now
why don't we just make the context window unlimited
because more context usually means more work
at a high level
the model has to consider the context while choosing each next token
so when the context grows
the computation needed per step can increase
you can feel this in real tools
replies can get slower apps may warn you about limits
some interfaces nudge you towards shorter prompts
also different models can offer different context sizes
and those choices often involve trade offs
sometimes you get a bigger window but higher cost
sometimes you get speed but a smaller window
and sometimes you get good enough memory
because the app summarizes or compresses old messages
so yes a bigger context window can improve results in many cases
but it's not free
it's an engineering constraint you can't just wish away
so bigger windows help but you can still hit the ceiling
and if you do here's what that looks like in real chats
okay what actually happens when you hit the limit
a few common things sometimes
the tool refuses your request and tells you the context is too long
sometimes it silently drops or summarises older parts of the chat
sometimes it produces an answer that sounds confident
but ignores earlier rules or facts you already gave it
and that last one is the most confusing
because it feels like the model is lying
but a simpler explanation is often it can't see what it needs anymore
here's a practical diagnostic you can use today
when the model starts contradicting your earlier constraints
first
suspect that those constraints aren't in its active context anymore
that's not you being paranoid
that's you being realistic about a limited window
so if that's what hitting the ceiling looks like
what can you actually do about it
now let's turn all of this into habits you can actually use
first work in stages
ask for an outline then pick one section
then expand it this keeps each turn smaller and easier to keep in view
second keep your instructions compact
instead of writing a long story about what you want
try a tiny constraints block like tone friendly format
bullets must include three examples
must avoid spoilers third
refresh the context on purpose
every few turns ask the model to summarize the key facts and decisions
in five to eight bullets
then paste that summary back into the chat when you continue
that's like pinning the important notes onto the whiteboard
so they don't get erased fourth
don't paste everything paste what matters
if you're asking about one paragraph
share one paragraph if you're asking about one scene
share one scene you'll usually get better results with smaller
cleaner inputs so next time an AI forgets
don't just get annoyed get strategic
remember the hidden rule in many chat tools
you're spending tokens on the way in and on the way out
inside one fixed context window
try this the very next time you use a chat tool
ask for a short outline then expand one part at a time
keep a running bullet summary and paste it forward
now I'm curious
what's the biggest thing you've tried to do in a single prompt
was it rewriting a document
planning a project studying for an exam
tell me in the comments
because I read them and I borrow your ideas for future videos
and if you want simple explanations of how these tools actually work
tokens context
windows hallucinations
and how to get more reliable answers
hit subscribe
I've got more videos coming to help you get better results with LLMs
even if you never write a line of code